Most developers and creators think that
the biggest benefit of using AI is that
it does the work for you. And that's
what I thought too. But I was completely
wrong about what actually makes AI such
a gamecher. It's an upgrade that
fundamentally changes how I learn and
how I create. In this video, I'll tell
you about how I broke through my ceiling
as a product designer and developer in
ways that I never even expected. I want
you to see AI not as a replacement for
you or for your skills, but as a massive
upgrade that can make you much better at
your craft, and that can lead you to
make a much greater impact on your
business, on your career, and for you as
a creator and a builder. Let's get into
it. Here's the trap that I almost fell
into in the early days of AI. You know,
most people see AI as potentially
replacing themselves, replacing their
job, replacing their skills. And for me,
to be honest, I was a little bit excited
about that at first because as a product
builder and a business owner, I like the
idea of being able to build and ship
things efficiently. The idea of
completely delegating the work to an AI
is pretty exciting for someone like me.
That line of thinking actually leads to
disappointment because when you actually
try to use AI to create things to write
code for you or to write a article like
it's just not good enough. It it can't
possibly do as good of a job as you can
as a creator or as a builder or as a
professional with real human experience.
And so then we're actually back to where
we were in the pre-AII days where we as
humans were just doing the best work
that we possibly can on our own without
any of the benefits of this AI
revolution, if you will. And so that was
the trap that I fell into early on. It's
actually why I feel like I was a bit
slow to the game of starting to adopt
AI, especially in my coding and
development workflow as I'm building
products. But now I'm starting to
incorporate it into everything else I do
from writing to video production. And
I'm only realizing now, especially in my
product development workflow where I'm
using AI heavily using tools like Cursor
and Claude, that it's time for me to
catch up. It's time for me to make up
for all that lost time and start to use
AI in a way that actually makes me
better at my craft. Now, here is the
unexpected breakthrough that I realized
sometime in the past year before AI,
before I started using it in my
day-to-day workflow. I found that my
skills as a developer and a designer and
a creator, they were stagnating. I was
plateaued. And I realize now why that
was. In the pre-ai days, I stuck to
building things and creating things that
I already knew how to build and how to
create because I've done those things
before. I was in my comfort zone and I
stayed in my comfort zone without
pushing myself beyond my limits. Now,
why is that? Well, it's because as a
product developer and as a entrepreneur
who's trying to bring new products into
the market and get them into the hands
of customers, shipping speed is like
everything to me, right? I really care
about being able to design, develop,
create, and ship new products into the
market so that I can get the feedback
from customers and then iterate and move
forward. And that desire to move fast is
also what pushed me to stay within my
comfort zone and stay within building
the same types of features, the same
types of products over and over again
because I knew how to ship those really,
really fast. And I knew that anytime I
ventured into unknown territory, you
know, new technologies or being
ambitious to build something that I've
never built
before, that's always a slower process
because there's the extra time that I
would need to take to learn, to read up,
to watch tutorials, to read books.
That's a much slower process because of
that learning curve. And so that's what
actually led me to shy away from going
after new, more cutting edge ideas. And
who knows what's even on the other side
of those ideas and what I might have
learned beyond those and what other
products I might have uncovered because
I stayed on my plateau. I stayed at my
nice comfortable fast shipping speed of
what I knew how to build. Fast forward
to today where I have AI fully embedded
in my design and development workflow.
Now I have the freedom to be much more
ambitious about what I decide to build,
even if it's venturing into totally new
territory. Because thanks to AI, now I
can compress the time and the effort to
familiarize with new territory and to
orient myself in learning new ways to
build things. You know, whereas before
it required hours and days and weeks of
reading and watching tutorials and going
on Stack Overflow, remember that site?
And now I can prompt an AI to lead the
way, show me an example, start to build
the thing that I've never built before,
and then I can go in and actually learn.
I can see the dots that the AI connected
for me and I can actually read the code
and start to put it together. And this
is in my own product. So I'm learning
within the context of what I'm actually
trying to build. Now again getting back
to the misconception that the first pass
out of an AI is going to be perfect.
It's not. It never is. But then that
cycle of diving into what the AI put
together and then crafting it and
shaping it and correcting it and putting
my human stamp on it, my taste comes
into play. And that's where the true
value is found, right? I can take the
first pass from what the AI built and I
can learn and start to familiarize with
like, okay, this is the road map to
getting into this new territory that
I've never touched before. But there are
a few things that are off. It's not
actually achieving the goal of the
product or the job to be done. AI
doesn't necessarily know that. And so
that's where my experience, my skills,
my taste as the human creator behind
this thing, I can start to shape what
the AI has laid out before me. Get it
from that 70 or 80% of the way there to
a final product that's 100% ready to
ship. It's polished. It has my stamp and
my design built into it. And I'm off to
the races. So, it makes me think about,
you know, what has actually changed for
me or for my business now that I've
embraced and adopted AI in my creative
workflow on a day-to-day basis. I'm able
to venture into newer, more cutting edge
territory for me that I haven't touched
before. And what that means is that it
can uncover new product ideas and
breakthroughs that I wouldn't have
actually reached before. And that can
make a real impact on the products that
I ship and the success that my business
has. I can feel it every day and I can
even see it in some of the work that I'm
doing today. But on a personal level, I
feel like I have completely busted out
of that plateau that I was in for
several years there before I started
using AI on a regular basis. I don't
feel like my skills as a developer and a
designer are stagnating anymore. Every
single day, I feel like I'm leveling up
in some way because again, I can use AI
as my guide into this uncharted
territory for me. And now I've gained
that experience. I start to see those
patterns. I can start to connect dots
that weren't there before. And now I'm
actually growing as a creator and as a
professional. That obviously starts to
build and rebuild my confidence in my
ability to create, my ability to ship
products, and my ability to build a
business. So, how can you make this same
leap that I made over the past year or
two? Well, it starts with getting over
that misconception that AI is here to
just do all the work for you. It's not.
You can start to see AI more as a
creative collaborator, a partner that is
here to help you level up your craft.
You know, the new creative cycle that I
like to think about now is prompt,
learn,
improve, ship, and then repeat. So
prompting AI to lead the way into a new
area or a new thing that you want to
build and then instead of blindly
trusting what the AI has put together,
actually go in and read it and review it
because that's where the improvement
stage comes in. That's where you and
your craft and your experience come into
play. And then finally, you come to a
shippable product that can actually make
an impact. If you want to see what this
is looking like for me in practice on a
day-to-day basis, a couple weeks ago, I
made a video showing how I'm using
Cursor in my product development
workflow. Now, how I'm using Cursor and
any of these other AI tools keeps
changing from month to month and it
keeps improving. That's the other really
exciting thing about this. But yeah,
check out that video to see where I'm at
currently. And if there's anything else
that you'd like to see me cover here on
the channel, drop a comment, let me
know. and I'll see you on the next one.